Estes family papers, Inclusive: 1853-1996, undated, Bulk: 1861-1864
Baylor University, The Texas Collection
Estes family papers
Inclusive: 1853-1996, undated, Bulk: 1861-1864
Baylor University, The Texas Collection http://www.baylor.edu/lib/texas/
187
Estes, Aaron
1 document box.
The Estes family papers contain Civil War correspondence from Aaron Estes, soldier in the 10th Texas Infantry. Other materials in the collection include legal and financial papers.
Administrative Information
Biography/Profile
Aaron Douglas Estes (1820-1864) was born on 1820 May 10 to Hiram M. Estes (1797-1854) and Lucy Anna Richardson Estes (1799-1845) in Franklin County, Tennessee. He married Elizabeth Lucretia Wilson Estes, originally from Alabama, in Morgan County, Missouri, in 1838. They came to Texas in 1840, and settled in McLennan county, though they later moved close to Hillsboro in Hill County. They had nine children together.
When the Civil War came, Aaron Estes enlisted into Company B, 10th Texas Infantry, under Colonel Allison Nelson. The regiment was captured at Arkansas Post on 1863 January 11. Estes would have been imprisoned with the rest of his regiment for a time in Camp Douglas, Chicago, a Union prisoner of war camp, until they were exchanged and sent south.
After being exchanged, the regiment was consolidated with the 6th Texas Infantry and the 15th Texas Cavalry (dismounted) and assigned to Cleburne's division, Army of Tennessee. Estes and his unit participated in battles at Chickamauga and Chattanooga and the Atlanta Campaign. Aaron Estes was killed in the Battle of Jonesborough on 1864 August 31, the final battle of the Atlanta Campaign.
Scope and Content
The Estes family papers contain correspondence, legal papers, sales receipts, tax receipts, muster rolls, land surveys, and a hair album. The letters include information about the 10th Texas Infantry's defense of Arkansas Post. One letter describes Estes' experience at Camp Douglass prisoner of war camp before he and the rest of his unit were exchanged. The letters then describe the 10th Texas' involvement in the Atlanta campaign as part of Granbury's Texas Brigade, Cleburne's Division. The letters end before the Battle of Jonesborough on August 31, where Aaron Estes was killed.
Arrangement
Prior to current processing, the collection was housed in folders with titles. No dates were present on the folders. Paper clips, staples, or other fasteners had already been removed.
Currently, the collection is contained in two series: I. Aaron Estes Civil War Letters and II. Collected Family Materials. Materials are arranged chronologically, and most letters have a copy of the letter filed with them.
Access Restrictions
All requests for copying of materials must be submitted to The Texas Collection in writing. Please use the Request Form for Copying Materials sheet. Unpublished materials authored or otherwise produced by the creator (s) of this collection are in the public domain. There are no restrictions on use. Copyright status for other collection materials is unknown. Transmission or reproduction of materials protected by U.S. Copyright Law (Title 17, U.S.C.) beyond that allowed by fair use requires the written permission of the copyright owners. Works not in the public domain cannot be commercially exploited without permission of the copyright owners. Responsibility for any use rests exclusively with the user.
Acquisition Information
Accession No. 187. Acquired 1972-02-14
Related Resources
Related references
Find a Grave, Inc. "Aaron Douglas Estes, Sr." Memorial #51364723. Databases. Accessed 2017 February 14.
Hamilton, Matthew K. "Tenth Texas Infantry." Handbook of Texas Online. Accessed 2017 February 14.
The American Civil War Research Database. "Soldier Data: Aaron Estes." Accessed 2017 February 14.
U.S. Bureau of the Census. 1860 United States Census, s.v. "Aaron Estes," Division Hill, McLennan County, Texas. Heritage Quest Online. Accessed 2017 February 14.
Index Terms
Places
United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Correspondence.
Genres
Correspondence.
- Aaron Estes Civil War Letters, 1861-1996; 1
  Administrative Information
  Biography/Profile
  This series contains letters to and from Aaron Estes, a Confederate soldier during the Civil War. Also included are muster rolls and indexes of cemeteries. This series is in poor condition.
  - Correspondence, 1861 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence, 1862 January (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 1862 February-May (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1862 September-December (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 1863-1864 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Correspondence, 1876, undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Transcriptions, 1862-1863 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Transcriptions, 1861-1864 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Muster Rolls, 1861-1863 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Index to Confederate Veterans Buried in Pioneer Cemetery, Eastland County, Texas, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Index to Confederate Veterans Buried in Merriman Cemetery, Eastland County, Texas, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Collected Family Materials, 1850-1996, undated; 2
  This series contains financial documents, programs from an event at a cemetery, and a hair album. This series is in average condition.
  - Legal, 1850-1872 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Tally Sheet, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Financial, 1853-1872 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Family Hair Album, undated (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Programs, Pioneer Cemetery, Eastland County, Texas, 1996 (Box 1, Folder 16)